<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Your Neighborhood Scientist</title>
<link>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/</link>
<atom:link href="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>cultivating community-based conversations around science, science policy, and scientists</description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.40</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Why I love the science I do: the magic of unlocking the secrets of our bodies</title>
  <dc:creator>Francesca Costabile, PhD</dc:creator>
  <link>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/magic-of-unlocking-secrets-of-our-bodies/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>There’s a special feeling that comes with every discovery in science, but for me, that joy started long before I even realized it would become my life’s work. It began with a simple yet profound moment, when I first went to the doctor for blood work. I was a child, probably 3 years old, but my curiosity was undeniable. I remember feeling a surge of excitement when I learned about the cells inside me, the tiny warriors, ready to fight off invaders and keep me healthy. I wanted to know everything about them. Why did I have so many different kinds? What did they do? I remember asking my father to make sure he booked the appointment for my blood work every year on my birthday – that was the present I wanted!</p>
<p>This fascination with the inner workings of my own body sparked my love for science. As I got older, that curiosity eventually led me to a career as a researcher studying the immune system. I find it so exciting that the answers we’re looking for often lie right inside us. For example, my research focuses on how we can stimulate the cells that the body already produces to fight against harmful entities like cancer or dangerous pathogens. It’s like discovering that the solutions to our biggest health challenges are already available to us, we just need to learn how to unlock their potential. Think about it: your body has an incredible army of cells, each with a specific job to do. The magic of immunology is understanding how these cells work together, and how we can harness them to fight diseases more effectively. It’s a bit like being the <strong>conductor of a symphony</strong>, where you get to bring all these parts into harmony to create something powerful. And what excites me the most is that this research could lead to breakthroughs that affect future generations. Imagine a world where you can activate your body’s defenses to prevent diseases like cancer before they even start. That’s the kind of impact I’m striving for.</p>
<div class="flex-container align-center">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/magic-of-unlocking-secrets-of-our-bodies/conductor.png" height="500" class="figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Illustrated by <a href="https://www.holydiode.com/">Holy Diode</a> (<a href="https://www.instagram.com/holy.diode/"><span class="citation" data-cites="holydiode">@holydiode</span></a>)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<p>I am currently a senior researcher at Penn in the Radiation Oncology department, which has been a dream come true, but it certainly wasn’t an easy path. Becoming a scientist required years of study, sleepless nights in the lab, and constant learning and adapting to new challenges. There were times I wanted to give up. Sometimes, I still wish I could have more free time for the things I love, like traveling, singing, dancing, or painting. But every time I get frustrated, I remind myself of the bigger picture: the potential to make a real difference, to change the lives of patients, and to contribute to the scientific community.</p>
<div style="float: right; margin: 5px;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/magic-of-unlocking-secrets-of-our-bodies/fc.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="200"></p>
<figcaption>Francesca in the laboratory.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<p>There’s often a misconception that science is a lonely pursuit, but the truth is, it’s a community effort. I’m deeply grateful to the people who believed in me along the way, including mentors, colleagues, and family. Without their support, I wouldn’t be at Penn today, working to unlock the secrets of the immune system. Here, I’m fortunate to be part of a team that pushes the boundaries of what we know, helping each other with experiments, and sharing with each other successes and challenges of our science. The work we do is driven by a collective belief that, together, we can make the world a better place through discovery and innovation.</p>
<p>As I look ahead to the future of science, I’m filled with excitement not just for what we can accomplish in my lifetime, but for what the next generation of scientists will achieve. One of my greatest joys will be passing on the knowledge I’ve gained to the young scientists who will carry the torch forward. Teaching and mentoring are integral parts of my journey, because, just like others did for me, I want to inspire the next wave of innovators to push the boundaries of what’s possible. Science isn’t just about asking questions – it’s about cultivating the curiosity, creativity, and perseverance to find the answers. It’s about turning what seems like an impossible dream into something tangible, something that can change lives. Whether you’re studying the immune system, exploring the depths of space, or unlocking the secrets of the brain, science is about making the world a better place through knowledge and discovery. Every day in the lab is a new opportunity to learn, to grow, and to make an impact. I feel fortunate to be part of this incredible journey, and I can’t wait to see where it leads. I hope that, through my work, I can share a little bit of that joy and inspire others to be just as excited about the world of science as I am.</p>
<hr>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled" title="About the author" style="">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
About the author
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Francesca is a postdoctoral researcher in the Radiation Oncology department at the University of Pennsylvania. With a master’s in Biology and a PhD in Clinical and Experimental Immunology, when she is not busy trying to find the cure for cancer, Francesca enjoys singing, dancing, painting, cooking, and spending time in nature.</p>
</div>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>curiosity</category>
  <category>immunology</category>
  <category>community</category>
  <category>science joy</category>
  <guid>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/magic-of-unlocking-secrets-of-our-bodies/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/magic-of-unlocking-secrets-of-our-bodies/conductor.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Worms and Flies and Fungi, Oh My</title>
  <dc:creator>Mikel D. Haggadone, PhD</dc:creator>
  <link>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/worms-flies-fungi-oh-my/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Is scientific research valuable and worth funding if it doesn’t directly impact human health? This question has been vaulted to the forefront of American discourse on science and its support by taxpayer money. I must be honest: as a basic science researcher (we’ll get to what this means in a minute), I’m frustrated by the premise of this question. The answer is so obvious to me: a resounding “YES!”, and my reasoning is both philosophical and practical. I <em>believe</em> – though I recognize and respect opposition to this belief – that there is intrinsic value in knowledge. However, I also <em>know</em> that funding research simply intended to understand more about the natural world has profoundly shaped how we treat and cure disease. As I write this, I feel responsible for acknowledging a personal blind spot while conveying an overlooked and yet critically important sentiment: we, as scientists, have not done a very good job of communicating the importance of our scientific inquisition to you, the public. So, while I am frustrated by the ongoing valuation of my intellectual passions and life’s work as a scientist, I recognize that you deserve to know why what I do is valuable, how it improves your life, and why it’s worthy of taxpayer support.</p>
<p>In this discussion, I want to drive home a very important point: throughout history, scientific curiosity and inquisition – even when not intended to directly impact human health – has created the foundation of knowledge needed to make medical breakthroughs possible today. You might be surprised (and fascinated) to find out that seemingly tangential discoveries made in organisms such as worms, flies, and fungi have fundamentally improved our understanding of human biology and what goes awry during disease. Importantly, at the time of discovery, the value of this research was unknowable, but with time its application has become invaluable. Therefore, funding basic science research does not simply support our curiosity as scientists, but it is also an indispensable long-term investment in your health. Let’s discuss why.</p>
<p>Before we take a step back into history and showcase the impact of some seminal basic science discoveries, let’s first cover relevant terminology. In a very general sense, scientific research can be broken down into two arms: basic research and translational research. Basic science research is, at its very core, driven by curiosity and intended to understand more about the natural world. Its aim isn’t to cure human disease per se, but rather to ask (and answer) the question of how and why things are the way they are. I’m defining this in a very general way to be inclusive of the many different domains of scientific research, but some example questions that researchers may ask and experimentally seek to answer are as follows: How do dietary nutrients impact the way your immune cells function? How do the cells in your body divide and what are the signals that cause them to do this? How does the brain integrate and process sensory information so that your behavior aligns with physiological and environmental needs? What makes plants sensitive or resistant to stress imposed by the environment, whether that be from pathogens (i.e., microbes that can infect and damage them) or extreme weather patterns?</p>
<p>You can imagine the endlessness of this line of questioning, which makes science so exciting! However, perhaps you can also appreciate that while none of these questions alone are posed to directly advance human health, application of the discoveries resulting from them absolutely could and often do. This is where translational science takes center stage. At its core, translational science is the applied arm of research, leveraging our fundamental knowledge of how things work – again, discovered through basic experimentation – to then design studies that are directly intended to improve well-being and/or treat disease. As an example, let’s take the first scientific question posed above, which just so happens to be the line of inquiry guiding my research: How do dietary nutrients impact the way your immune cells function?</p>
<p>To answer this question, I work with both human and mouse samples to experimentally determine what metabolic fuels – the carbohydrates, fats, and amino acids acquired through the foods you eat – are needed for your immune cells to carry out their intended protective functions. When I design experiments in the lab, I don’t do so with any specific disease in mind. Rather, I focus on the exploratory value of gaining knowledge, and I allow my curiosity to conceptually advance the scientific conclusions supported by my data. I, as we say, “follow the science” by simply allowing my empirical observations to instruct the next steps in my experimentation. As a result of this approach, in the three years of my postdoctoral fellowship research, my team has uncovered many fascinating insights into the nutritional safeguards and vulnerabilities of the immune system, and we are becoming well-positioned to begin translating these findings into clinically meaningful contexts like infection and cancer when your immune cells need to do their job in metabolically hostile environments. Will the research I’m doing today save your life tomorrow? Absolutely not, but it does have the potential to revolutionize how we might nutritionally and therapeutically target immune cell metabolism to improve human health in just a matter of years, which is why my work has been so generously funded by organizations and agencies like the American Heart Association and National Institutes of Health.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/worms-flies-fungi-oh-my/mdh-lab.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Mikel in his laboratory conducting an experiment. Credit: Ryan Reiss</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<hr>
<p>Thinking big picture, what I want to underscore here is that this relationship between the basic and translational arms of science is necessarily synergistic. Each arm informs and accelerates the other, and both must <strong>coexist</strong> for medical breakthroughs to happen. It should come as no surprise then that the United States’ financial commitment to basic science research is the reason why we have been a global powerhouse in the health sciences. In essence, your taxpayer support is the lifeline that has created opportunities for scientists like me to transform curiosity into the life-saving tools, technologies, and medicines that in turn benefit you. But don’t just take my word for it, let’s turn to history to show you how.</p>
<p>Most cancer therapies, regardless of their mechanisms of action, share the same primary goal: to cause cancer cells to die. At face value, this seems rather simple, right? The complexity arises from the way that a cancer cell dies, which can come in many different flavors, each with its own set of biological triggers, genetic requirements, and consequences for how surrounding cells interpret and respond to it. These different “flavors” collectively comprise the study of programmed cell death (also referred to as regulated cell death), and many major advances in cancer therapy can be attributed to scientific discoveries that have enhanced our ability to kill tumor cells by targeting an exploitable and suitable regulated cell death modality. What may come as a surprise to you, however, is that the study of programmed cell death originated from basic science research performed using <em>Caenorhabditis elegans</em> (<em>C. elegans</em>), a small roundworm with simple anatomy that has long served as an experimental tool to study how animals develop.</p>
<p>After Dr.&nbsp;Sydney Brenner’s work in the 1960s established <em>C. elegans</em> as a model organism for developmental biology research, the work of two scientists, Drs. John Sulston and H. Robert Horvitz (and others not mentioned here), determined that programmed cell death is a naturally occurring biological process with specific genetic requirements for roundworms to normally grow<span class="citation" data-cites="sulston_post-embryonic_1977 yuan_c_1993"><sup>1,2</sup></span>. Yes, you read that right: during embryogenesis, we need certain cells to die for our organs and tissues to properly develop (otherwise, we’d all have webbed toes and fingers)! This Nobel Prize-winning research set the stage for subsequent discovery of analogous genes and pathways in humans, and it has profoundly shaped our understanding of how and why programmed cell death is both developmentally important and therapeutically exploitable to kill unwanted cells. Let’s zoom out for a second. How remarkable is it that scientific curiosity for the development of a roundworm has so meaningfully advanced our understanding of human biology and influenced how we treat our most challenging diseases? <em>This</em> is the value of basic science.</p>
<p>Research using fruit flies tells a similar tale. We all know that our immune cells detect invading microbes and help to protect us against infectious diseases. The cells comprising our innate immune system (i.e., the body’s first line of defense against pathogens) can do so in a remarkably rapid way. But how do they achieve this? In the late 1980s, a prominent immunologist by the name of Dr.&nbsp;Charles Janeway first theorized that our innate immune system must use receptor molecules that readily detect specific molecular “patterns” intrinsic to invading microbes (e.g., components of their cell wall), thereby making them distinguishable from the patterns that make up our own body. It was an intriguing hypothesis that would explain why our immune system is so good at quickly discerning self (i.e., us) vs.&nbsp;non-self (i.e., pathogenic bugs), but it lacked sound experimental evidence.</p>
<p>In a series of landmark discoveries made throughout the 1990s (including those from one of Dr.&nbsp;Janeway’s postdoctoral trainees, a distinguished immunologist, Dr.&nbsp;Ruslan Medzhitov), scientists cleverly used genetic analyses of a known human immune signaling molecule to uncover similar elements in other species. The hope at the time was to uncover new genetic data that could help point researchers toward the human gene(s) encoding Janeway’s theorized “pattern-recognition receptors”. Shockingly, what they found in <em>Drosophila melanogaster</em>, colloquially known as the fruit fly, was a gene named <em>Toll</em>, which was both genetically similar to the already characterized immune signaling molecule <u>and</u> other human genes previously unknown to researchers. These novel genetic sequences – again, brought to light by comparative genetics in the fruit fly – were subsequently termed Toll-like receptor genes and experimentally demonstrated to encode the very pattern-recognition machinery that Janeway hypothesized would exist throughout the human innate immune system<span class="citation" data-cites="gay_drosophila_1991 medzhitov_human_1997"><sup>3,4</sup></span>. Let’s zoom out again and take a moment to appreciate how amazing this is: because of the herculean efforts made by countless basic scientists to study and functionally characterize genes comprising the fruit fly genome, the stage was set for researchers like Dr. Janeway to uncover the biological basis of pathogen detection and protection against infectious disease. Not only did this research fundamentally advance our basic understanding of the human immune system, but it also fueled the development of therapeutics that improve our ability to fight off pathogens and cancers and dampen the immune response when inflammation goes awry. Here again, <em>this</em> is the value of basic science, and it’s saving lives every single day.</p>
<p>To be candid, if I didn’t have so many experiments to complete at this stage in my career, I’d genuinely love to write a book highlighting more stories like those showcased above – the list is endless. Indeed, not captured here are the many discoveries made using yeast genetics to understand more about how and when our cells divide, or insights into how zebrafish have helped to better characterize the genetic basis of many human diseases. Nevertheless, what I hope you can take away from this essay is that curiosity-driven research has profoundly changed our lives for the better, and it’s simply a consequence of researchers asking the questions, “How?” and “Why?” Research is our passion, and we are indebted to society for supporting our life’s work. Truly, we thank <strong>you</strong>. In turn, I hope you can see the value in what we contribute to you and your health, even when our research questions appear tangential or irrelevant. Because understanding more about the natural world is not only what gives our professional lives purpose and meaning, it is also the foundation of your well-being and the fabric of what has made the United States a leader in biomedical research. Basic science is the lifeblood of medical innovation, and it needs your support now more than ever.</p>
<p>Does this sentiment resonate with you? If so, share your excitement and tell someone what you learned about science today.</p>
<hr>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled" title="About the author" style="">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
About the author
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Mikel Haggadone received his PhD in Immunology from the University of Michigan Medical School in 2021 and is now completing his Postdoctoral Fellowship at the University of Pennsylvania Perelman School of Medicine in the laboratory of Dr.&nbsp;Sunny Shin. In addition to his love for research, Mike is a passionate educator and mentor for Penn’s First Exposure to Research in the Biological Sciences (FERBS) Program, where he has the privilege to support an amazing cohort of undergraduate students in their journey toward becoming future leaders in science and medicine. Outside of academia, Mike cherishes his time with his partner, Dr.&nbsp;Audrey Drotos, in their never-ending pursuit of excellent food and amazing trails to adventure on.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/worms-flies-fungi-oh-my/mdh-trail.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Mikel at the grand canyon. Credit: Adam Hughes, <a href="https://www.preracepodcast.com/">PreRacePodcast Productions</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body" data-entry-spacing="0" data-line-spacing="2">
<div id="ref-sulston_post-embryonic_1977" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">1. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Sulston, J. E. &amp; Horvitz, H. R. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/0012-1606(77)90158-0">Post-embryonic cell lineages of the nematode, <span><em>Caenorhabditis</em></span><span> <em>Elegans</em></span></a>. <em>Developmental Biology</em> <strong>56</strong>, 110–156 (1977).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-yuan_c_1993" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">2. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Yuan, J., Shaham, S., Ledoux, S., Ellis, H. M. &amp; Horvitz, H. R. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/0092-8674(93)90485-9">The <span>C</span>. Elegans cell death gene <span><em>Ced-3</em></span> encodes a protein similar to mammalian interleukin-1<span><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cbeta"></span>-converting enzyme</a>. <em>Cell</em> <strong>75</strong>, 641–652 (1993).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-gay_drosophila_1991" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">3. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Gay, N. J. &amp; Keith, F. J. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/351355b0">Drosophila <span>Toll</span> and <span>IL-1</span> receptor</a>. <em>Nature</em> <strong>351</strong>, 355–356 (1991).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-medzhitov_human_1997" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">4. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Medzhitov, R., Preston-Hurlburt, P. &amp; Janeway, C. A. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/41131">A human homologue of the <span>Drosophila Toll</span> protein signals activation of adaptive immunity</a>. <em>Nature</em> <strong>388</strong>, 394–397 (1997).</div>
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>basic science</category>
  <category>model organisms</category>
  <category>science history</category>
  <guid>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/worms-flies-fungi-oh-my/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/worms-flies-fungi-oh-my/mdh-lab.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>NIH Intramural Research: from my first job to saving my mom’s life</title>
  <dc:creator>Brooke Wolford</dc:creator>
  <link>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/nih-intramural-first-job-saving-mom/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>On May 25, 2023, I held my mom’s hand while she signed consent forms to enroll as the 94th patient in a clinical trial at the National Institutes of Health (NIH). We were sitting in the NIH Clinical Center, the world’s largest hospital dedicated to clinical research. Some call it the “House of Hope.” We do too.</p>
<p>A decade before the ink dried on those consent forms, I began my first post-college job within sight of the “House of Hope.” I was hired in a full-time research position through the NIH Intramural <a href="https://www.training.nih.gov/research-training/pb/pb/">Postbaccalaureate Program</a>. This is a training opportunity for recent college graduates considering graduate or professional school in healthcare and STEM fields. I worked in Building 50, the Louis Stokes Laboratories, which houses the laboratories of the National Human Genome Research Institute, one of 27 Institutes and Centers of the NIH. These Institutes compose the NIH Intramural Program, which is supported by 11% of the NIH budget and funds the nearly 6,000 scientists on the NIH main campus in Bethesda, Maryland, and other smaller NIH campuses across the US.</p>
<p>I spent two exciting and impactful years working in the laboratory of Dr. Francis Collins, the NIH Director at the time. With my mentors, I studied how genetic variation can lead to Type 2 Diabetes. This experience laid the groundwork for my career as a geneticist, and, unbeknownst to me at the time, it prepared me for my role as a caregiver of an NIH patient. I knew how to search <a href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</a> for treatment opportunities. I trusted her team of providers. My familiarity with the NIH and biomedical research enabled me to advocate for and support my mom during this journey.</p>
<p>The world’s experts on my mom’s rare disease, lymphomatoid granulomatosis (LYG), work at the National Cancer Institute of the NIH. In the summer of 2023, they gave my mom life-saving, but grueling, chemotherapy, to rid her body of the rapidly multiplying cells caused by Epstein Barr Virus (EBV). This is the virus that causes mono and lives dormant in about 90% of us. In my mom, Epstein Barr Virus is active and causing problems. Because it is a rare disease, it has taken over 30 years to enroll enough patients to really understand the way this disease works and how to treat it.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/nih-intramural-first-job-saving-mom/bnw-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Brooke and her mom after she completed her last of 6 rounds of chemotherapy at the NIH Clinical Center.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<hr>
<p>Before this clinical trial, scientific publications established the median survival for LYG as 14 months, because it wasn’t clear how to treat these patients. When she was diagnosed, this trial felt like our only hope. Her private insurance was unlikely to cover medicine not yet demonstrated to be the standard of care for LYG. Determining standard of care for a rare disease is time consuming and expensive! This is the kind of life-changing work the NIH Intramural Program supports. Led by Dr.&nbsp;Christopher Melani, the clinical trial successfully established a set of treatments as standard of care, publishing a median survival of 12.1 years<span class="citation" data-cites="melani_interferon_2023"><sup>1</sup></span>. This result will facilitate better treatment of LYG at hospitals across the country and globally.</p>
<p>Clinical trials like the one that saved my mom fall under the NIH’s Intramural Research program. Thanks to taxpayer dollars, my mom’s treatment was paid for. So was the fuel she used to drive the 7 hours to and from rural North Carolina. Budget cuts have reduced the amount she is reimbursed for her accommodations in Maryland, but this is the price we will pay for more years together. For NIH patients facing hardships, <a href="https://www.friendsatnih.org/">the Friends of Patients at the NIH</a> is a charitable organization that helps with emotional, financial, and logistical support.</p>
<p>Fast forward to January 2025, and my mom was one treatment into her second clinical trial at the NIH. After a year in remission, her disease was back, so the doctors were trying something new. As the new Presidential administration came to Washington, Executive Orders caused communication and travel bans, as well as funding freezes at the NIH. We were incredibly concerned how new policy might affect her ability to continue treatment. As of now, her trial is running as expected. However, the NIH Intramural Postbaccalaureate Program which once employed me, and provides valuable training to the next generation of our nation’s scientists and physicians, is paused pending guidance from the Department of Health and Human Services.</p>
<p>As a scientist and a daughter of a rare disease warrior, the NIH Intramural Research Program has changed my life. It is my deepest wish that the NIH continues to be a model of excellence for biomedical research by treating patients, training scientists, making discoveries, stimulating the economy, and providing hope for decades to come. I hope the “House of Hope” will be there for you, too, if you one day need it.</p>
<hr>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled" title="About the author" style="">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
About the author
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p><a href="https://bnwolford.github.io/">Brooke</a> is a Marie Skłodowska-Curie Postdoctoral Fellow at the Norwegian University of Science and Technology. She spends her days studying the genetics of heart disease, snuggling her Basenjis, and learning to speak Norwegian. Snakker du norsk?</p>
</div>
</div>
<p><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/nih-intramural-first-job-saving-mom/bnw-2.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body" data-entry-spacing="0" data-line-spacing="2">
<div id="ref-melani_interferon_2023" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">1. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Melani, C. <em>et al.</em> <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S2352-3026(23)00029-7">Interferon alfa-2b in patients with low-grade lymphomatoid granulomatosis and chemotherapy with <span>DA-EPOCH-R</span> in patients with high-grade lymphomatoid granulomatosis: An open-label, single-centre, phase 2 trial</a>. <em>The Lancet Haematology</em> <strong>10</strong>, e346–e358 (2023).</div>
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>NIH</category>
  <category>clinical trials</category>
  <category>family</category>
  <guid>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/nih-intramural-first-job-saving-mom/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/nih-intramural-first-job-saving-mom/bnw-1.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Introducing Your Neighborhood Scientist</title>
  <dc:creator>Audrey Drotos</dc:creator>
  <link>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/introducing-your-neighborhood-scientist/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Hello!</p>
<p>My name is Audrey, and I’m a neuroscientist. I study brain cells: how they talk to each other, what they’re saying, and how they help us figure out what’s going on in our environments.</p>
<p>I started this newsletter because I’m increasingly concerned about how science and medical research is viewed by the public. There’s been a shift over the last few years in how I hear people talk about science, and it’s at odds with what I see and experience in my day-to-day life as a researcher. I feel so excited about the amount of progress being made in the scientific community, from treatments for HIV and pediatric cancers to new vaccines for RSV and cancer, but I sense a growing unease with these same discoveries amongst the general public, with an increase in discussion of conspiracy theories (like the myth that vaccines cause autism), a decrease in the number of people who support public health measures backed by science (like fluoride in our drinking water), and general growing distrust in the scientific and medical communities.</p>
<p>I’m sure there are many factors at play that have widened this chasm between scientists and non-scientists, but I think one is a misunderstanding of how science works: how basic science informs medical breakthroughs, how science is funded in the US, and the role that pharmaceutical companies and medical professionals play. I think most people would be surprised to hear that much of what we know about human genetics comes from studying yeast and worms, or that the US federal government funds upwards of 90% of the research happening at universities across the US, both public and private.</p>
<p>In addition, I think another big driver of this gap between scientists and the general public is a misunderstanding of who scientists are. I’ve worked in academia for the last nine years of my life, and the people I work with are some of the most compassionate, hard-working, dedicated individuals, who sacrifice many years of their lives to bring new advancements into the world that will make our lives better. As I read Facebook comments and see the rhetoric on TV, I often find myself wishing I could just show people the scientists I know: I wish I could bring you to lab and show you the people I work with every day, show you how hard they are working, and show you how the work they do makes your life better and our communities stronger.</p>
<p>Your Neighborhood Scientist is my initiative to do just that: to tell the world how the scientists in your neighborhoods are working hard—just like you—to leave a positive mark on this world. I started this newsletter because I believe that we can work together to show the world that science is critical to the health and well-being of our communities. Changing this rhetoric is no small task, and I think it starts with information: how does this all work? How does the work scientists do every day, funded by taxpayers, eventually end up handed to you over the counter at your local pharmacy in a paper bag that contains life-saving medication? How does it strengthen our economy? How does it enhance our national defense and emergency preparedness?</p>
<p>I also realize that if you’re reading this newsletter, you’re likely someone who is somewhat interested in science. I probably don’t have to convince you too much that we should fund basic science research, and that scientists are incredible, genuine people who are trying to make the world a better place. But why do you think that? Maybe it’s because you understand the intricacies of science, and you know about NIH institutes and CAR-T cell pathways. Or maybe not: most likely, you believe in science because you know and trust me, Audrey, your neighborhood scientist. People’s beliefs are not informed by facts and information: they are informed by feelings and trust.</p>
<p>In our newsletter, we’ll work to fill the science information gap by stressing the importance of basic science research and providing information about how it works, and I hope that you do learn more about the work scientists do. But to me, it’s not important if you remember specific details, like what an indirect rate is at the NIH. What’s important is that you feel inspired to tell other people that know and trust you about how important you think science is. Perhaps over time they might even become convinced that they, too, should advocate for scientists and good science policy. The goal is to provide the knowledge that scientists are working hard to make the world a better place and use this as a vehicle to spread positive feelings and trust surrounding science, because these are the things that change people’s minds.</p>
<p>I don’t know what will ultimately happen with this journey, but if you read all the way through: thank you. Tell someone who trusts you about science today, and see you in a couple weeks.</p>
<hr>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled" title="About the author" style="">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
About the author
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Audrey Drotos is a Neuroscientist at the University of Pennsylvania where she studies how we hear. She is a founder of Your Neighborhood Scientist. Outside of science and writing, she enjoys long-distance trail running, thrifting vintage jackets, buying really good apples at the farmer’s market, and curling up with a great book, preferably one by Ed Yong.</p>
<p><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/introducing-your-neighborhood-scientist/acd.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>intro</category>
  <category>policy</category>
  <guid>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/introducing-your-neighborhood-scientist/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
