<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Your Neighborhood Scientist</title>
<link>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/</link>
<atom:link href="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>cultivating community-based conversations around science, science policy, and scientists</description>
<generator>quarto-1.7.32</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Happy July 4th!</title>
  <dc:creator>Scientists in Your Neighborhood</dc:creator>
  <link>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Here at Your Neighborhood Scientist, we’re excited to highlight American patriotism in a way you might not always think about: scientific research. If you’re an American taxpayer, your tax dollars currently go towards the National Institutes of Health (NIH), which is the world’s largest funder of biomedical research. As a result, the US is the primary driver of science and technology innovation in the world. Between 2010 and 2019, 354 out of 356 of drugs approved by the FDA received funding from the NIH during their <a href="https://www.bentley.edu/news/new-study-shows-nih-investment-new-drug-approvals-comparable-investment-pharmaceutical">development</a> – a whopping 99.4%. These medications included Keytruda, a breakthrough cancer treatment, Trikafta, a life-changing therapy for many with cystic fibrosis, and Imbruvica, a breakthrough therapy for blood cancers. As your neighborhood scientists, we want you to feel proud to be American this July 4th because those breakthroughs came from your tax dollars – and as scientists, we’re proud to be entrusted with those dollars to generate tomorrow’s medical breakthroughs.</p>
<p>We recently asked some of our neighborhood scientists why they are proud to do taxpayer-funded scientific research in the US. In their answers, we hope that you, too, can feel some American pride in science this July 4th. Here are a few:</p>
<div class="flex-container align-center">
<p><a href="ScientistQuotes.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 4"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/ScientistQuotes.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:60.0%" alt="Quotes from scientists about why they are proud to perform taxpayer-funded research in the US. The quotes are available in their entirety in the article below."></a></p>
</div>
<hr>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip no-icon callout-titled" style="" title="I get to make discoveries about how nature works">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
I get to make discoveries about how nature works
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>“As a US scientist, I get to make discoveries about how nature works with creative, intelligent, hard-working people from all around the world. US taxpayer-funded research grants and fellowships are pushing science forward from a knowledge perspective, and also by training the next generation of scientists and shifting the culture of academia to welcome people from all walks of life, helping the world to benefit from their unique contributions. I’m proud to make basic science discoveries that can one day inform medical breakthroughs (like the scientists who contribute to mRNA vaccines, and treatments for chronic illnesses and genetic conditions).”</p>
<div class="align-center">
<p>– Anonymous Graduate Student</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-warning no-icon callout-titled" style="" title="My work helps understand relapse">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
My work helps understand relapse
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>“My work helps understand relapse and why stress causes us to seek out certain rewards (substances, comfort food, bingeing tv) — my work informs clinicians, counselors, and therapists to help people struggling with addiction.”</p>
<div class="align-center">
<p>– Katie Emery</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled" style="" title="I want to protect people">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
I want to protect people
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>“I work on developing vaccines and looking into immunity in general against influenza virus. I’m proud to perform taxpayer-funded research in the US because I know my work could eventually lead to life-saving vaccines. I want to protect people from infectious diseases and vaccines are one of the best ways to do that.”</p>
<div class="align-center">
<p>– Dr.&nbsp;Gabrielle Scher</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-caution no-icon callout-titled" style="" title="Performing research is my most cherished expression of creativity">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Performing research is my most cherished expression of creativity
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>“Performing research is my most cherished expression of creativity! It brings me so much joy to develop new ideas, tools, and technologies that fundamentally advance our basic knowledge of mammalian biology and have profound potential to improve human health. I’m proud to do this work in a country that has consistently been a global leader in biomedical research!”</p>
<div class="align-center">
<p>– Mikel Haggadone, PhD</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip no-icon callout-titled" style="" title="For the good of the public">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
For the good of the public
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>“I am proud to do research because my colleagues and I are learning more about the world we all live in and how it works. I believe that this understanding can help us tackle problems in the world like disease but also I think the knowledge alone is exciting. I am proud that the research I do is taxpayer-funded because it means it is not beholden to a corporation but for the good of the public, even beyond our borders. In a time of”America First” this is a way our country is still giving to the world.”</p>
<div class="align-center">
<p>– Emma Thornton-Kolbe</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-warning no-icon callout-titled" style="" title="I am proud to be a source of hope">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
I am proud to be a source of hope
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>“Every day, I am reminded of the fact that we do not understand enough about the diseases and conditions we encounter on a regular basis. For example, Alzheimer’s disease – almost everyone knows someone or is related to someone with Alzheimer’s disease. We have made remarkable progress in diagnosing this condition, but we still have few truly effective treatments. Research has the potential to change this, and I am proud to be among those working to change the status quo. When people receive the diagnosis for a condition such as Alzheimer’s, it can be devastating, both to them and to their loved ones. Still, many people are comforted and even reassured by the fact that we are working on a solution… even if we do not have one today, there is hope for tomorrow. I am proud to be a source of hope for these people, their families, and their friends.”</p>
<div class="align-center">
<p>– Sami Barmada</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled" style="" title="The technology is desperately needed">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
The technology is desperately needed
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>“I do research on technology for people with disabilities. Market-driven forces would say that there are not enough people with severe disabilities to support this research. But the technology is desperately needed. And so many of our modern conveniences have grown from research into special-purpose technology that no one realized would be wildly popular once it became available.”</p>
<div class="align-center">
<p>– Jane E. Huggins, PhD</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-caution no-icon callout-titled" style="" title="For the development of new medications and therapies">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
For the development of new medications and therapies
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>“I study the activity of immune cells in antiphospholipid syndrome, an autoimmune disease that can cause dangerous blood clots to form. Antiphospholipid syndrome is poorly understood, and many patients experience strokes, cardiovascular issues, and other life-threatening complications of disease. I’m proud to contribute to our knowledge of antiphospholipid syndrome and other immune-mediated diseases, to allow for the development of new medications and therapies to better treat patients around the world.”</p>
<div class="align-center">
<p>– Thalia Newman, PhD Student</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Over the next week, we’ll continue to highlight the incredible scientists that do this government-funded research and the citizens who benefit and support it, from high school teachers to those obtaining medical treatment through NIH-funded clinical trials. If you’re not already, you can follow us on <a href="https://www.instagram.com/your.neighborhoodscientist">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/neighborhoodscientist">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/your-neighborhood-scientist">LinkedIn</a>, and <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/your.neighborhoodscientist.org">Bluesky</a>. We hope that you’ll share with your neighbors why funding science is patriotic, and we hope you feel proud, too. Because those scientific breakthroughs? They’re made in the USA – thanks to you.</p>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout-ncol="3">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="img/07-04_various-graphics/MakesAmericaHealthy.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 4"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-04_various-graphics/MakesAmericaHealthy.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="img/07-04_various-graphics/AmericanTaxpayer.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 4"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-04_various-graphics/AmericanTaxpayer.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="img/07-04_various-graphics/WorldsLargestFunder.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 4"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-04_various-graphics/WorldsLargestFunder.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<section id="july-5th-2025" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="july-5th-2025">July 5th, 2025</h2>
<p>Science and research innovations are everywhere – if you just know where to look! Almost everything you see in the natural environment, we know more about because of scientific research. Why do the leaves fall from the trees in the fall? Why do birds fly south? What makes the tides go in and out every day?</p>
<p>This knowledge is important because it helps us plan for things like hurricanes and figure out how to set up home foundations so they don’t sink into the ground. It also helps us develop innovations that help us preserve the natural world – like window stickers to avoid migrating bird collisions.</p>
<p>Today, we’re highlighting scientists who love the taxpayer-funded work they do because it helps them understand the world around us. How has science helped you understand the world around you?</p>
<div class="flex-container align-center">
<p><a href="img/07-05_understand-the-world/UnderstandTheWorld-01.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 5"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-05_understand-the-world/UnderstandTheWorld-01.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:60.0%"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout-ncol="3">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="img/07-05_understand-the-world/UnderstandTheWorld-02.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 5"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-05_understand-the-world/UnderstandTheWorld-02.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="img/07-05_understand-the-world/UnderstandTheWorld-03.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 5"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-05_understand-the-world/UnderstandTheWorld-03.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="img/07-05_understand-the-world/UnderstandTheWorld-04.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 5"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-05_understand-the-world/UnderstandTheWorld-04.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="july-6th-2025" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="july-6th-2025">July 6th, 2025</h2>
<p>Between 2010 and 2019, 354 out of 356 of drugs approved by the FDA received from NIH funding during their development – a whopping 99.4%. These medications included Keytruda, a breakthrough cancer treatment, Trikafta, a life-changing therapy for many with cystic fibrosis, and Imbruvica, a breakthrough therapy for blood cancers.</p>
<p>Today, we’re highlighting some of the scientists who do this NIH-funded work – the ones who are pushing the boundaries of what we know to cure diseases and solve today’s medical mysteries so that we can have more tomorrows.</p>
<p>Do you or a loved one benefit from medical advances that originated from NIH-funded research (if you’ve ever taken a medication or been to a hospital, that answer is yes!) Feel free to share your stories below, and why you’re proud to fund this work with your tax dollars!</p>
<div class="flex-container align-center">
<p><a href="img/07-06_cure-diseases/CureDiseases-01.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 6"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-06_cure-diseases/CureDiseases-01.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:60.0%"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout-ncol="3">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="img/07-06_cure-diseases/CureDiseases-02.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 6"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-06_cure-diseases/CureDiseases-02.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="img/07-06_cure-diseases/CureDiseases-03.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 6"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-06_cure-diseases/CureDiseases-03.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="img/07-06_cure-diseases/CureDiseases-04.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 6"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-06_cure-diseases/CureDiseases-04.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="img/07-06_cure-diseases/CureDiseases-05.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 6"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-06_cure-diseases/CureDiseases-05.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="img/07-06_cure-diseases/CureDiseases-06.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 6"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-06_cure-diseases/CureDiseases-06.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="img/07-06_cure-diseases/CureDiseases-07.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 6"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-06_cure-diseases/CureDiseases-07.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="july-7th-2025" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="july-7th-2025">July 7th, 2025</h2>
<p>When you think of creativity, you probably think of artists and writers. But what about scientists? For many, scientific research provides an opportunity to ask creative questions and generate new ways to answer them. In doing so, scientists are able to tackle today’s problems from unique angles and provide solutions that haven’t been used before. Ultimately, this can generate novel disease cures and treatment options for people that didn’t previously exist.</p>
<p>Today, we’re highlighting scientists who love the creative freedom offered by basic science research funded by the National Institutes of Health and National Science Foundation – the two largest funders of science research. We are inspired by their commitment to finding creative solutions to tough problems, and we hope you are, too.</p>
<div class="flex-container align-center">
<p><a href="img/07-07_creativity/Creativity-01.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 7"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-07_creativity/Creativity-01.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:60.0%"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout-ncol="4">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 25.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="img/07-07_creativity/Creativity-02.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 7"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-07_creativity/Creativity-02.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 25.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="img/07-07_creativity/Creativity-03.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 7"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-07_creativity/Creativity-03.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 25.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="img/07-07_creativity/Creativity-04.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 7"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-07_creativity/Creativity-04.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 25.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="img/07-07_creativity/Creativity-05.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 7"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-07_creativity/Creativity-05.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="july-8th-2025" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="july-8th-2025">July 8th, 2025</h2>
<p>The two largest funders of research in the U.S. – the National Institutes of Health and the National Science Foundation – are funded by taxpayer dollars. This research is behind every medical breakthrough we see today, from the drugs on the market to new imaging methods to detect cancers to robotics that make surgery less invasive.</p>
<p>That also means that these breakthroughs are all because of <em>you</em>. If you pay taxes in the U.S., every cancer cure and Alzheimer’s drug and addiction treatment option is all thanks to you and the funding from your tax dollars for the NIH and NSF. And here at Your Neighborhood Scientist, we think that’s something to be proud of.</p>
<div class="flex-container align-center">
<p><a href="img/07-08_give-back/GiveBack-01.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 8"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-08_give-back/GiveBack-01.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:60.0%"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout-ncol="3">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="img/07-08_give-back/GiveBack-02.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 8"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-08_give-back/GiveBack-02.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="img/07-08_give-back/GiveBack-03.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 8"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-08_give-back/GiveBack-03.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="img/07-08_give-back/GiveBack-04.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 8"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-08_give-back/GiveBack-04.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="july-9th-2025" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="july-9th-2025">July 9th, 2025</h2>
<p>We asked scientists across the U.S. why they’re proud to do science here, and their answers ranged from curing diseases to giving back to understanding the world around us. Many also mentioned that they love to do science here because it’s <em>hard</em>. U.S. science is held to an extremely high standard of excellence – grant funding is competitive, publishing requires multiple reviews from peers, and studies have to be designed rigorously. That high standard drives scientists to do excellent work with the critical eye that is needed to develop cures for today’s most complex diseases, from cancer and autoimmune disorders to genetic conditions and dementia.</p>
<div class="flex-container align-center">
<p><a href="img/07-09_high-standard/HighStandard-01.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 9"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-09_high-standard/HighStandard-01.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:60.0%"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout-ncol="3">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="img/07-09_high-standard/HighStandard-02.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 9"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-09_high-standard/HighStandard-02.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="img/07-09_high-standard/HighStandard-03.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 9"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-09_high-standard/HighStandard-03.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="img/07-09_high-standard/HighStandard-04.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 9"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-09_high-standard/HighStandard-04.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="july-10th-2025" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="july-10th-2025">July 10th, 2025</h2>
<p>If you or a loved one has ever received a challenging medical diagnosis, you know that navigating a diagnosis like cancer or a genetic condition can be daunting. When we asked U.S. scientists why they love the science they do, many shared that their work is able to be a source of hope for those who have been diagnosed with challenging medical conditions. Each day, new treatment options become available that turn previously devastating diagnoses into a hiccup in life. Scientists love the work they do because they can provide hope – because they know that their work can increase the quality of life and can even save the lives of those impacted by the diseases they study.</p>
<div class="flex-container align-center">
<p><a href="img/07-10_source-of-hope/SourceOfHope-01.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 10"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-10_source-of-hope/SourceOfHope-01.png" class="img-fluid" style="width:60.0%"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel" data-layout-ncol="3">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="img/07-10_source-of-hope/SourceOfHope-02.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 10"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-10_source-of-hope/SourceOfHope-02.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="img/07-10_source-of-hope/SourceOfHope-03.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 10"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-10_source-of-hope/SourceOfHope-03.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 33.3%;justify-content: center;">
<p><a href="img/07-10_source-of-hope/SourceOfHope-04.png" class="lightbox" data-gallery="July 10"><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/img/07-10_source-of-hope/SourceOfHope-04.png" class="img-fluid"></a></p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<hr>
<p>That’s a wrap for our feature celebrating American science! We hope that you, too, can feel some pride that your taxpayer dollars support such amazing scientists and their impactful work.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>July 4th</category>
  <category>US Independence Day</category>
  <category>Research Funding</category>
  <guid>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/july-4th-independence-day/ScientistQuotes.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="180" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>From Pipette Tips to Pandemic Surveillance: A Scientist’s Evolution</title>
  <dc:creator>Ruchi Korde</dc:creator>
  <link>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/pandemic-wastewater-surveillance/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>When you grow up with parents working in specialized fields, you usually take one of two paths: veer off in a totally different direction or follow in their footsteps. I fall into the second category. My mom started working toward her PhD when I was three years old, and that’s when I fell in love with science.</p>
<p>By the time I was five, she was taking me into the lab for a few hours each week when her experiments ran long. While she worked, I sat in the corner of the lab, entertained by conducting small chores. Even the smallest glove size was too large for my five-year-old hands, but I wore them and happily filled pipette tip boxes making fun new patterns. When I was ten, she defended her thesis. My dad and I got her a card that read, “We don’t know what you did, but we know it was impressive!” Now, as a PhD student myself, I do know what she did, and just how impressive it really was.</p>
<p>Her dedication to science and research shaped my childhood, and the lab she worked in was a welcoming, inspiring place. The grad students read books with me when my mother was busy conducting experiments, and I considered them to be family. They all seemed so wise and shared the same passion for science that really shaped my childhood. By high school, I knew I wanted to pursue research at a high level and eventually earn a PhD. I applied to, and was accepted by, the same university where she earned hers. Before I even registered for classes, I started working as an undergraduate researcher in the very lab where she’d done her thesis work. Her former advisor was thrilled to have me there, continuing the family legacy.</p>
<p>At that point, I wasn’t sure exactly what kind of research I wanted to do. Like many early science students, I had big dreams: curing cancer with virus-delivered drugs or discovering a new super-antibiotic to wipe out all harmful bacteria. But in that lab, I found a different calling.</p>
<p>The lab focused on water quality microbiology. We were trying to figure out what was increasing bacterial levels in recreational water bodies, like beaches, rivers, and lakes. It felt like we were poop detectives. Was it a deer with a stomach ache? A leaky sewage pipe? We’d investigate by heading to the scene (wherever local agencies directed us), collecting evidence (water samples), analyzing them (using tests to identify genetic markers from animals or humans), and reporting back our findings. I loved the intersection of microbiology, environmental science, and public health.</p>
<p>Then the pandemic hit.</p>
<p>When cases of COVID-19 started increasing, scientists realized that they needed a fast and inexpensive method to identify areas with large numbers of infected individuals, and they turned to wastewater surveillance. As someone already working with wastewater, I understood the untapped potential of the information it held. When someone is infected with a microorganism, that organism often shows up in their waste. Before 2020, wastewater surveillance was mainly used to track poliovirus, an infectious disease that spreads through contaminated food, water, or contact with an infected person. Most people don’t get sick from polio, but in serious cases, it can cause paralysis or even death. Even though polio doesn’t usually cause stomach symptoms, the virus appears in large amounts in feces and can survive for long periods in wastewater. In fact, wastewater surveillance for polio has been in use since 1988, helping detect outbreaks both in countries where the virus was thought to be eradicated and where it’s still common.</p>
<div class="flex-container align-center">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/pandemic-wastewater-surveillance/ground-water-germs.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption>Illustration by Kunga Nyima Drotos</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<p>The first scientists to track SARS-CoV-2 in wastewater were in the Netherlands. They successfully estimated how many people were infected in a city, before clinical case numbers started to rise. Though COVID-19 doesn’t typically cause gastrointestinal symptoms, high levels of SARS-CoV-2 were found in patients’ fecal samples. That breakthrough prompted governments around the world to fund and expand wastewater surveillance programs<span class="citation" data-cites="medema_presence_2020"><sup>1</sup></span>.</p>
<p>Building on that success, scientists began looking even deeper. Today, we use wastewater surveillance to monitor not just viruses like Influenza A, mpox, and norovirus, but also fungi like Candida auris (which resists many antifungal treatments), and even antibiotic resistance genes.</p>
<p>And we’re not stopping there.</p>
<p>A newer approach, wastewater sequencing, goes beyond identifying whether a virus is present. It looks at which version is present. For example, in January 2021, there were two variants of SARS-CoV-2 circulating, alpha and beta, and it was crucial to differentiate between them because beta was believed to be more infectious. If alpha could infect two people, beta might infect three. That may not seem like a huge difference, but it matters at the population level. Sequencing can give public health officials early warnings about which variants were spreading and helped shape decisions to slow the spread.</p>
<p>I found this combination of sequencing and surveillance fascinating, and it’s what led me to where I am now. I’m currently a second-year PhD student designing a method to sequence different Influenza A sub-clades from wastewater. A sub-clade is a group of influenza viruses that have similar genetic backgrounds, and being able to sort a virus in this way can help track its circulation. Influenza viruses are classified based on their genetic makeup, particularly a segment called “H.” You may have heard of H5N1 or bird flu in the news. This specific subtype has been around since the late 1990s, but recently a new sub-clade has emerged, one that can infect cows<span class="citation" data-cites="american_veterinary_medical_association_avian_2025 caserta_spillover_2024 mostafa_avian_2024"><sup>2–4</sup></span>. That’s raising alarms about whether it could jump to other mammals, like humans.</p>
<p>Right now, wastewater surveillance can detect if H5N1 is present. But what we can’t yet confirm is whether it’s the more dangerous sub-clade circulating in cows, or just one that’s commonly circulating in birds. That’s where my work comes in. I hope to use wastewater sequencing to tell the difference. If we can do that, we’ll not only help prevent the spread of bird flu, but also reduce unnecessary fear when people hear that H5N1 was detected in their local wastewater. I am working on a protocol that will identify sources of fecal matter in wastewater and the sub-clade of influenza A virus that is circulating. This protocol can eventually be implemented across the country and potentially globally to use in response to detections of H5N1 in wastewater.</p>
<p>To me, the role of a scientist is to expand the knowledge in my field in a way that directly benefits my community. Research like my own has led to discoveries that have saved millions of lives. As I learned from my mother early on, science is about understanding how the world works, and using that understanding to create a better, safer, and more informed society.</p>
<hr>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled" title="About the author" style="">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
About the author
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Ruchi Korde is a second year PhD candidate in the Department of Microbiology and Immunology at the University of Michigan Medical School. They have a Bachelor’s degree in Microbiology with a minor in General Public Health. Outside of the lab, Ruchi enjoys trying new restaurants and watching Formula 1 races.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="flex-container align-center">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/pandemic-wastewater-surveillance/ruchi-korde.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption>Ruchi next to a replica of the Broad Street Pump in London, a reminder of the severe cholera outbreak in 1854 where John Snow hypothesized that contaminated water from a particular pump was the source of the outbreak, rather than the popular theory that the infectious agent was transmitted by “miasma” or bad air. Snow’s work shaped the modern epidemiology field as we know it.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body" data-entry-spacing="0" data-line-spacing="2">
<div id="ref-medema_presence_2020" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">1. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Medema, G., Heijnen, L., Elsinga, G., Italiaander, R. &amp; Brouwer, A. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.estlett.0c00357">Presence of <span>SARS-Coronavirus-2 RNA</span> in <span>Sewage</span> and <span>Correlation</span> with <span>Reported COVID-19 Prevalence</span> in the <span>Early Stage</span> of the <span>Epidemic</span> in <span>The Netherlands</span></a>. <em>Environ. Sci. Technol. Lett.</em> <strong>7</strong>, 511–516 (2020).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-american_veterinary_medical_association_avian_2025" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">2. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Association, A. V. M. <a href="https://www.avma.org/resources-tools/animal-health-and-welfare/animal-health/avian-influenza/avian-influenza-virus-type-h5n1-us-dairy-cattle">Avian influenza virus type <span>A</span> (<span>H5N1</span>) in <span>U</span>.<span>S</span>. Dairy cattle</a>. (2025).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-caserta_spillover_2024" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">3. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Caserta, L. C. <em>et al.</em> <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-024-07849-4">Spillover of highly pathogenic avian influenza <span>H5N1</span> virus to dairy cattle</a>. <em>Nature</em> <strong>634</strong>, 669–676 (2024).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-mostafa_avian_2024" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">4. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Mostafa, A. <em>et al.</em> <a href="https://doi.org/10.1128/mbio.02542-24">Avian influenza <span>A</span> (<span>H5N1</span>) virus in dairy cattle: Origin, evolution, and cross-species transmission</a>. <em>mBio</em> <strong>15</strong>, e02542–24 (2024).</div>
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Microbiology</category>
  <category>Epidemiology</category>
  <category>Wastewater Surveillance</category>
  <category>Family</category>
  <guid>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/pandemic-wastewater-surveillance/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/pandemic-wastewater-surveillance/ground-water-germs.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>When the air we breathe is unfriendly</title>
  <dc:creator>Lizbeth F. Gómez, PhD, MPH</dc:creator>
  <link>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/the-air-we-breathe/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>There’s a moment most days when I step outside my front door and pause, just for a second, to notice how the air feels. Some days with the arrival of spring it’s crisp and welcoming, carrying the scent of freshly turned soil or blooming lilacs. Other days, it’s heavy. Laced with exhaust from engines idling down the block or the faint hum of an air conditioner kicking into gear. For the one in every twelve neighbors who live with asthma<span class="citation" data-cites="american_lung_association_asthma_2024"><sup>1</sup></span>, that heaviness can make the simple act of breathing feel like a chore. Asthma is what happens when our airways become overly sensitive and reactive to our environment, including things like pollen, dust, cold air or pollution. When someone has asthma, these environmental triggers tend to produce airway tightening and swelling, which can make breathing difficult and create a feeling of breathlessness that can be genuinely frightening.</p>
<p>Over the past decade, I’ve moved between classrooms, clinics, and conferences learning and trying to understand how the tiny particles we inhale each day shape our lung health and how they do so differently across communities. Today, as a postdoctoral researcher at the University of Pennsylvania, I study the invisible yet unavoidable connection between our environment and respiratory health. My research has focused on fine particles from traffic, factories, and even backyard grills, known to scientists as fine particulate matter or PM. For people living with asthma, these tiny particles can have a huge impact on their day to day life. For instance, on days when these microscopic pollutants are high, people living with asthma tend to reach for their inhalers far more often, and neighborhoods with higher pollution levels see a significant increase in asthma-related emergency visits<span class="citation" data-cites="us_epa_health_2016"><sup>2</sup></span>. The connection is clear: the quality of the air directly shapes our health.</p>
<p>However, asthma does not affect people equally. Through my research, I’ve learned that it comes down to how already-sensitive airways react to irritation. When someone with asthma inhales air pollutants, these particles act like tiny irritants that trigger an exaggerated immune response. Their airways, already primed to overreact, become even more inflamed and constricted. What fascinates me most in my data analysis is how this sensitivity varies even among people with asthma, depending on factors like their specific triggers, the medications they’re taking, and even most surprising, the neighborhoods they live in.</p>
<div class="flex-container align-center">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/the-air-we-breathe/illustration.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:80.0%"></p>
<figcaption>Illustrated by <a href="https://www.holydiode.com/">Holy Diode</a> (<a href="https://www.instagram.com/holy.diode/">@holydiode</a>)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<p>Asthma is not simply a story of invisible particles and scientific measurements. It’s also about lived experiences. About kids who hesitate on playgrounds, friends who limit their outings on smoky wildfire days, hazy summer evenings, and neighbors who rearrange their days based on air quality alerts. Asthma brings to light something deeply human: our vulnerability to the environment we live in. What strikes me most as a scientist is how changeable this situation really is. While genetics do matter, our environment and the air we collectively breathe often tip the scale between health and illness. In recent years, innovative treatments tailored to individuals’ allergic profiles and specific environmental triggers have become increasingly available, significantly reducing hospital visits. At a community level, we’ve learned that neighborhoods with more green spaces, parks, trees, and community gardens have lower asthma rates. These are practical and attainable local solutions that, if well funded and advocated for, can benefit everyone.</p>
<p>Even at home, we can improve our indoor air quality through seemingly modest steps like maintaining good ventilation, choosing household plants known to absorb pollutants, or routinely checking for allergens such as mold or dust mites. These steps may seem small, yet together they can significantly ease the daily struggles of people living with asthma. Asthma is a reminder that air doesn’t respect fences or boundaries. What circulates through one home inevitably touches another. In this interconnectedness lies a powerful opportunity to combine scientific understanding with community-driven actions. In the community-engaged work that I have done, I consistently champion the idea that we can collectively make our neighborhoods healthier by making our voices heard to policymakers who, at the end of the day, can enact meaningful changes when it comes to regulating pollution.</p>
<p>As a researcher, my goal is to help develop treatments that specifically consider air pollution and other environmental factors. In the future, I hope to see doctors and scientists routinely working together, using air-quality data to personalize asthma management so that treatments aren’t just responding to symptoms, but actively preventing them. The hope is that one day, our neighborhoods will be places where air pollution no longer dictates the quality of our health, and where breathing safely isn’t an aspiration, but the everyday reality we all enjoy.</p>
<hr>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled" title="About the author" style="">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
About the author
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/lizbeth-gomez/">Lizbeth F. Gómez</a> is an asthma researcher and environmental epidemiologist postdoctoral fellow in the Division of Pulmonary, Allergy and Critical Care Medicine at University of Pennsylvania. She has a master’s in Public Health in Molecular Epidemiology and a PhD in Environmental Health Sciences. When she isn’t cleaning data, you can find her tending her garden or experimenting with new recipes.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="flex-container align-center">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/the-air-we-breathe/LGomez-PR.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:90.0%"></p>
<figcaption>Lizbeth collecting community health data in San Juan, Puerto Rico (2019) as part of research examining respiratory health impacts in the aftermath of hurricanes Irma and Maria.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body" data-entry-spacing="0" data-line-spacing="2">
<div id="ref-american_lung_association_asthma_2024" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">1. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">American Lung Association. <a href="https://www.lung.org/research/trends-in-lung-disease/asthma-trends-brief/trends-and-burden">Asthma <span>Trends Brief</span>: <span>Asthma Trends</span> and <span>Burden</span></a>. (2024).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-us_epa_health_2016" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">2. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">US Environmental Protection Agency. <a href="https://www.epa.gov/pm-pollution/health-and-environmental-effects-particulate-matter-pm">Health and <span>Environmental Effects</span> of <span>Particulate Matter</span> (<span>PM</span>)</a>. (2016).</div>
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Air Quality</category>
  <category>Asthma</category>
  <category>Environment</category>
  <guid>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/the-air-we-breathe/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/the-air-we-breathe/illustration.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Timing is everything: how circadian clocks shape our health</title>
  <dc:creator>Ronan Lordan, PhD, MA</dc:creator>
  <link>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/timing-circadian-clocks/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Have you ever wondered why you wake when you do, sleep when you do, or eat when you do? Do you find you concentrate better in the morning? Has your doctor ever told you to take medicine at a certain time of day? We wake, we eat, sleep, and repeat.</p>
<p>We don’t ordinarily question why we do the things we do at specific times of the day. But beneath these patterns lies an exquisite internal orchestration of genes and proteins that we know to be circadian rhythms. These rhythms govern not just our behavior, but the timing of nearly every physiological process in our bodies. These near-24-hour rhythms, embedded in nearly every cell of the body, are critical to our survival and they evolved due to our need to adapt to the solar cycle. At the heart of this system is a master clock located in the suprachiasmatic nucleus (SCN), a tiny cluster of about 20,000 neurons in the hypothalamus. This master clock receives direct input from light-sensing cells in the retina and uses that signal to align our internal time with the external world,specifically, the 24-hour cycle of light and dark. Once synchronized, the SCN sends timing cues throughout the body, coordinating clocks in nearly every organ, including the liver, lungs, heart, and even skin. These cellular clocks run on a feedback loop of gene expression, turning on and off in rhythmic fashion. Together, they keep our bodies running on schedule. Over 20 genes govern this feedback loop, but two are particularly important. These “master clock genes” are called CLOCK and the slightly-less-catchy BMAL1, which I research.</p>
<p>Circadian rhythms aren’t just a human thing, they’re a universal timekeeping system found in everything from people and pets to plants and even tiny microbes. Whether it’s a flower opening at sunrise or bacteria timing their metabolic activity, life on Earth runs on internal clocks. And while the genes behind these rhythms vary, the purpose is the same: staying in sync with the day. The first to really notice and describe circadian rhythms was a French astronomer with a memorable name, Jean-Jacques d’Ortous de Mairan in 1729. He conducted a famous experiment with a mimosa plant (which opens its leaves during the day and closes them at night) and observed that the plant continued its leaf movements even when kept in constant darkness. This showed that the plant had an internal biological clock and that the plant wasn’t just reacting to sunlight. While de Mairan’s experiment was with a plant, not a human, he was the first human to document intrinsic rhythmic behavior tied to time. This laid the foundation for modern chronobiology, the study of biological rhythms. As for human circadian rhythms specifically, it wasn’t until much later, in the 20th century, that researchers like Jürgen Aschoff and Franz Halberg systematically studied and coined terms like “circadian”. Halberg is actually the one who coined the word “circadian” (from Latin circa diem, meaning “about a day”) in the 1950s.</p>
<figure class="figure">
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/eviOCC13Pt0?si=v6fjopskbWQy16dG" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay;
clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="">
</iframe>
<figcaption>
Circadian control of leaf movement by the Utah State University Crop Physiology Lab
</figcaption>
</figure>
<hr>
<p>In humans, this internal schedule manifests in countless ways. For example, core body temperature rises in the morning, peaking in the late afternoon before dropping again in preparation for sleep. Our metabolic processes, including how we absorb and store nutrients, are also time-sensitive, with studies showing that eating late at night can lead to greater weight gain and insulin resistance compared to eating earlier in the day, even when calorie intake is identical. Our moods, cognitive performance, and even social behaviors fluctuate with the clock. Studies have shown that reaction time, memory, and attention peak in the late morning to early afternoon, which has implications for everything from school start times to work productivity<span class="citation" data-cites="valdez_circadian_2019"><sup>1</sup></span>. Mental health, too, is intimately tied to circadian function. Individuals with mood disorders such as depression or bipolar disorder often show disrupted circadian rhythms, delayed sleep-wake cycles, irregular daily routines, or altered melatonin and cortisol patterns. Some non-pharmacological interventions, such as light therapy and chronotherapy (timing sleep and light exposure to reset rhythms), work by directly targeting the circadian system. Pharmacological interventions such as lithium also work by influencing the clock, but the mechanisms governing these effects are not fully understood and many patients do not respond to lithium. Until we fully understand these biological mechanisms, we can’t fully exploit their benefits. Maybe the time of day that we take lithium may increase its effectiveness and reduce side effects. Hence, funding basic research in circadian biology is critically important.</p>
<p>Perhaps more surprisingly, our immune system has its own clock. White blood cell counts fluctuate predictably throughout the day, and immune responses to infection vary by time of day. Vaccines have been shown to be more effective when administered in the morning, an insight that could inform public health strategies. Pain perception, too, has a rhythm, with sensitivity often peaking at night, a detail that may help explain why certain chronic pain conditions worsen in the evening.</p>
<p>These rhythms are not merely passive reflections of the day but active drivers of behavior and physiology. When our schedules fall out of sync with our biological clocks, a condition known as circadian misalignment, health consequences follow. Shift workers, for example, are at higher risk for metabolic syndrome, cardiovascular disease, and certain cancers. This is why it is so important to support basic scientific research, especially in a field like chronobiology, which has already uncovered many biological nuances leading to advancements in health care. Research from our lab suggests that men are at more risk than women from conditions linked to circadian misalignment and shift work<span class="citation" data-cites="anderson_sexual_2023"><sup>2</sup></span>. Jet lag, that temporary form of circadian disruption you feel after a long transatlantic flight into a different time zone, demonstrates how we feel the effects of desynchrony. But while jet lag may pass in days, chronic misalignment (from irregular sleep, social jet lag, or late-night lifestyles) can have lasting effects on health and well-being.</p>
<p>Understanding circadian rhythms gives us a new lens through which to view human behavior, not as a series of isolated choices, but as patterns deeply shaped by time. In the same way that gravity quietly shapes the motion of planets, circadian rhythms shape our days, often without our awareness. By aligning our behaviors more closely with these biological rhythms, from sleep and meal timing to exercise and work, we may unlock new ways to promote health, performance, and even happiness. And by supporting the science that reveals these rhythms, we invest in a future where timing becomes not just an afterthought, but a central pillar of medicine and public health.</p>
<div class="flex-container align-center">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/timing-circadian-clocks/ronan_illustration_nobg-01.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption>Illustration by Kunga Nyima Drotos</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<p>However, despite its relevance to virtually every aspect of health, circadian biology remains chronically underfunded. Much of what we know about these biological clocks comes from basic science research, long-term, curiosity-driven studies in fruit flies, mice, cells, and even plants that laid the foundation for today’s breakthroughs. To unlock the next generation of therapies and preventive strategies, we need to invest in this kind of fundamental research now. The science of time has never been timelier, and its potential to transform medicine is only just beginning, as seen in advances in chronomedicine.</p>
<p>Circadian medicine or chronomedicine, is the application of our understanding of biological rhythms to improve health. The field of chronomedicine is already beginning to reshape how we think about disease prevention, diagnosis, and treatment. Research has shown that the timing of everything from drug delivery to surgery can influence outcomes. For instance, chemotherapy given at certain times of day can be more effective and less toxic and blood pressure medications may work better when taken at night<span class="citation" data-cites="paschos_role_2010"><sup>3</sup></span>. This emerging field asks not just what treatment to give, but when, adding a powerful new layer to personalized medicine.</p>
<p>The foundation of these insights lies in decades of basic circadian research, including several landmark discoveries. The 2017 Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine recognized three scientists for uncovering the molecular machinery of the circadian clock, the feedback loop consisting of clock genes like PER, CRY, and BMAL1 that keep time within our cells. These breakthroughs, initially discovered in fruit flies, have since been shown to influence nearly every aspect of physiology in humans. What began as a curiosity about fruit fly behavior has opened the door to a revolution in understanding how timing governs health and disease.</p>
<p>In my research, I have been investigating the role of the clock in metabolism, exercise, and aging. Specifically, my research aims to determine how exercise may be beneficial as we age by influencing circadian rhythms. We investigate mice that genetically lack the clock gene, Bmal1. These mice as a consequence experience accelerated aging, sarcopenia-like muscle physiology (they have low muscle mass and muscle weakness), and poor health span and life span, showing how vitally important clock genes are for health. At our lab, led by Dr Garret A. FitzGerald at the University of Pennsylvania, we also focus on the effects of shiftwork on circadian rhythms and cardiometabolic health in both humans and animal models.</p>
<p>To unlock the next generation of therapies and preventive strategies, we need to invest in fundamental research now. The science of time and the circadian clock is not a niche biological curiosity, it is a foundational pillar of human health and disease. The transformative insights we’ve gained from the lab bench to the clinic, stem directly from decades of investment in basic science. Without sustained and expanded funding, we risk slowing progress at a moment when the potential for medical breakthroughs has never been greater. It has never been timelier to recognize the urgency and promise of chronobiology, which drives innovation in medicine, public health, and beyond.</p>
<div class="flex-container align-center">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/timing-circadian-clocks/Ronan_in_lab.JPG" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption>Ronan in the laboratory preparing for his next experiment.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<hr>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled" title="About the author" style="">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
About the author
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Ronan Lordan received his PhD in nutrition, pharmacology, and cardiovascular science from the University of Limerick (Ireland) in 2020. Dr Lordan conducted his postdoctoral research training in chronobiology at the Institute for Translational Medicine and Therapeutics (ITMAT), at the Perelman School of Medicine, University of Pennsylvania in the Laboratory of Dr Garret A. FitzGerald. Ronan is now a Research Associate researching circadian rhythms in aging. In addition to his pursuit of knowledge, Ronan is an educator and mentor. He holds a Masters in Teaching, Learning, and Scholarship and his thesis focused on the relationship between mentors and mentees and how that relationship is critical to the career of young scientists. He is a co-director of the ITMAT-FIRST translational research experience for aspiring young scientists. Ronan is a passionate science communicator and is the National Eastern Coordinator for <a href="https://pintofscience.us/">Pint of Science USA</a> covering Boston, New Haven, New York, and Philadelphia. Outside of academia, Ronan enjoys playing guitar, going to concerts, sipping coffee with a book, and traveling with his fiancée Samantha.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="flex-container align-center">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/timing-circadian-clocks/Paris.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:70.0%"></p>
<figcaption>Ronan &amp; Sam in Paris.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body" data-entry-spacing="0" data-line-spacing="2">
<div id="ref-valdez_circadian_2019" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">1. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Valdez, P. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6430172">Circadian <span>Rhythms</span> in <span>Attention</span></a>. <em>Yale J Biol Med</em> <strong>92</strong>, 81–92 (2019).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-anderson_sexual_2023" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">2. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Anderson, S. T. <em>et al.</em> <a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/scitranslmed.abo2022">Sexual dimorphism in the response to chronic circadian misalignment on a high-fat diet</a>. <em>Sci. Transl. Med.</em> <strong>15</strong>, eabo2022 (2023).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-paschos_role_2010" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">3. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Paschos, G. K., Baggs, J. E., Hogenesch, J. B. &amp; FitzGerald, G. A. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.pharmtox.010909.105621">The <span>Role</span> of <span>Clock Genes</span> in <span>Pharmacology</span></a>. <em>Annu. Rev. Pharmacol. Toxicol.</em> <strong>50</strong>, 187–214 (2010).</div>
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Circadian Rhythms</category>
  <category>Biological Clocks</category>
  <category>Basic Science</category>
  <guid>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/timing-circadian-clocks/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/timing-circadian-clocks/ronan_illustration_nobg-01.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="143" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Vax to the future: building a healthier tomorrow with vaccines</title>
  <dc:creator>Alyssa Maturen-Backlas, MSc</dc:creator>
  <link>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/building-healthier-tomorrow-vaccines/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Quiz time: What has been rigorously tested since 1796, extensively peer-reviewed, and saved over <a href="https://www.who.int/news/item/24-04-2024-global-immunization-efforts-have-saved-at-least-154-million-lives-over-the-past-50-years">154 million lives</a> in the past 50 years alone? And the answer is—vaccines! Vaccines have become a hot topic recently, but what exactly are they, and why are they so important? As a public health professional, these are some of the most common questions I get—and I love answering them! It gives me the chance to share evidence-based information so that people can make informed healthcare decisions for themselves and their loved ones.</p>
<p>Imagine it’s the 1870s. The Industrial Revolution is in full swing, bringing exciting new technologies. Factories are rising, cities are growing, and people are living closer together than ever before. But with inadequate sanitation, poor working conditions, and no modern medicine, diseases spread rapidly. One of the worst illnesses at the time? Smallpox. <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/smallpox/about/index.html">Smallpox was a highly contagious viral infection</a>, often spreading through airborne particles from coughs and sneezes. If you were unfortunate enough to catch it, you spend agonizing days with high fevers, painful rashes, pustules, and sometimes even death. Smallpox killed about 3 of every 10 people infected, and those who survived often experienced permanent disability, blindness, and scarring on the face. In its final 100 years, smallpox claimed an estimated 500 million lives. It was devastating—until science changed everything. Enter Edward Jenner, the doctor who developed the first <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/smallpox/about/history.html">smallpox vaccine</a>. His breakthrough was so effective that, by 1980, the World Health Organization declared smallpox <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/mmwr/preview/mmwrhtml/su48a7.htm#:~:text=Eradication%3A%20Permanent%20reduction%20to%20zero,nature%20or%20in%20the%20laboratory.">eradicated</a>. That means there are no more natural cases of smallpox anywhere in the world—a direct result of global vaccination efforts. But here’s the key: vaccines only work if people take them. In the 19th and 20th centuries, millions of people saw the need for vaccination and stepped up to protect themselves and their communities. Their willingness to get vaccinated changed history. It was this same community effort mindset that has helped <a href="https://ourworldindata.org/eradication-of-diseases">eradicate, or get close to eradicating</a> polio, diphtheria, pertussis, and several diseases that affect animals. When we all work together for the greater good we can make real and lasting change.</p>
<p>We might not be living in the 1800s, but infectious diseases haven’t disappeared. Yes, we have better sanitation and advanced medicine, but we also live in an era of overwhelming information—and misinformation. Some falsehoods are spread unintentionally (misinformation), while others are deliberately designed to deceive (disinformation). We also live in a time where internet personalities’ opinions on vaccination often weigh as heavily in public opinion as facts provided by the scientific experts. That’s where <a href="https://www.google.com/search?client=safari&amp;rls=en&amp;q=what+is+public+health&amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;oe=UTF-8">public health</a> comes in. Public health is about protecting and improving the health of people and communities. Some professionals focus on nutrition, others on disease tracking, and others—like me—on prevention. And the best tool we have for preventing disease? Vaccines.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://kidshealth.org/en/parents/immune.html#:~:text=How%20Does%20the%20Immune%20System,proteins%20lock%20onto%20specific%20antigens.">immune system</a> in your body is composed of various organs and is your body’s defense against infections. It is the major feature our bodies have to keep us safe. When a virus or bacteria enters your body, your immune system identifies it, attacks it, and remembers it for the future. Vaccines take advantage of this by introducing a harmless version of a virus or bacteria, <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/vaccines/basics/explaining-how-vaccines-work.html">allowing your body to build immunity</a> without you having to suffer through the actual disease. If you ever do encounter the real germ, your immune system will recognize it and respond much more efficiently, often preventing serious illness. But vaccines don’t just protect you. They help protect the community, especially those who are immunocompromised—people with weakened immune systems who can’t safely receive vaccines or fight infections effectively. This includes infants, the elderly, cancer patients, and people with autoimmune diseases, among others. When the majority of a community is vaccinated, diseases struggle to spread, creating a protective barrier known as herd immunity. This is how we protect our most vulnerable neighbors.</p>
<div class="flex-container align-center">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/building-healthier-tomorrow-vaccines/vaccine-summit_cropped.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:80.0%"></p>
<figcaption>Alyssa attending a vaccine summit in Atlanta with other vaccine nonprofits and coalitions from across the country</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<hr>
<p>The Immunization Alliance of Michigan is still in its early stages. As the leader of that vaccine coalition and nonprofit, I spend my days working on ensuring we can operate as an organization and provide meaningful education and services to traditionally under-served populations across Michigan. I do this by engaging with community members to see what their needs are, answering questions, and addressing concerns about vaccines. Many fears stem from misinformation, so I work with healthcare providers to give them resources and trainings on how to feel confident when talking about vaccines to their patients, create media content in various formats and languages to give to communities around the state, and I eventually hope to start working with the state legislature to get better vaccine education and access laws passed to improve health for everyone across the state. At its core, public health is about helping people live longer, healthier lives. But for that to happen, they need access to accurate, unbiased, and evidence-based information. Vaccine hesitancy that stems from misinformation inherently means that people aren’t truly making informed choices—because they don’t have all the facts! Right now, working in vaccine advocacy is tough. Political divisiveness and funding cuts make it feel like an uphill battle. It’s frustrating to see vital resources at risk when all we want is for people to be safe and healthy.</p>
<p>But despite the challenges, we keep showing up. We keep advocating. Because this work matters. If even one person reads the scientific research and recommendations we share and decides to get vaccinated to protect themselves or their community, that’s a win. Public health workers, including myself, will continue fighting for you, your family, and your community. We all want ourselves and our loved ones to be healthy. Getting vaccinated is one of the most effective ways to achieve that. It is so important that we continue to work together to prevent the spread of disease so that we can ensure a healthier future for everyone!</p>
<hr>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled" title="About the author" style="">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
About the author
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Alyssa Maturen-Backlas is the Executive Director of the non-profit Immunization Alliance of Michigan, which she runs on behalf of MDHHS and MPHI. When she’s not advocating for vaccines, Alyssa enjoys any and all outdoor recreation, pilates, and snuggling her corgi, Moose. It is her goal to visit every National Park and hike Mt. Everest.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="flex-container align-center quarto-layout-panel" data-layout-ncol="2">
<div class="quarto-layout-row">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/building-healthier-tomorrow-vaccines/ice-hotel_resampled.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:75.0%"></p>
<figcaption>Alyssa at the IceHotel in Sweden</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: flex-start;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/building-healthier-tomorrow-vaccines/crater-lake_cropped.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:100.0%"></p>
<figcaption>Alyssa hiking around Crater Lake National Park</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Vaccines</category>
  <category>Public Health</category>
  <category>History</category>
  <guid>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/building-healthier-tomorrow-vaccines/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 25 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/building-healthier-tomorrow-vaccines/vaccine-summit_cropped.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Why I love the science I do: the magic of unlocking the secrets of our bodies</title>
  <dc:creator>Francesca Costabile, PhD</dc:creator>
  <link>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/magic-of-unlocking-secrets-of-our-bodies/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>There’s a special feeling that comes with every discovery in science, but for me, that joy started long before I even realized it would become my life’s work. It began with a simple yet profound moment, when I first went to the doctor for blood work. I was a child, probably 3 years old, but my curiosity was undeniable. I remember feeling a surge of excitement when I learned about the cells inside me, the tiny warriors, ready to fight off invaders and keep me healthy. I wanted to know everything about them. Why did I have so many different kinds? What did they do? I remember asking my father to make sure he booked the appointment for my blood work every year on my birthday – that was the present I wanted!</p>
<p>This fascination with the inner workings of my own body sparked my love for science. As I got older, that curiosity eventually led me to a career as a researcher studying the immune system. I find it so exciting that the answers we’re looking for often lie right inside us. For example, my research focuses on how we can stimulate the cells that the body already produces to fight against harmful entities like cancer or dangerous pathogens. It’s like discovering that the solutions to our biggest health challenges are already available to us, we just need to learn how to unlock their potential. Think about it: your body has an incredible army of cells, each with a specific job to do. The magic of immunology is understanding how these cells work together, and how we can harness them to fight diseases more effectively. It’s a bit like being the <strong>conductor of a symphony</strong>, where you get to bring all these parts into harmony to create something powerful. And what excites me the most is that this research could lead to breakthroughs that affect future generations. Imagine a world where you can activate your body’s defenses to prevent diseases like cancer before they even start. That’s the kind of impact I’m striving for.</p>
<div class="flex-container align-center">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/magic-of-unlocking-secrets-of-our-bodies/conductor.png" height="500" class="figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Illustrated by <a href="https://www.holydiode.com/">Holy Diode</a> (<a href="https://www.instagram.com/holy.diode/"><span class="citation" data-cites="holydiode">@holydiode</span></a>)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<p>I am currently a senior researcher at Penn in the Radiation Oncology department, which has been a dream come true, but it certainly wasn’t an easy path. Becoming a scientist required years of study, sleepless nights in the lab, and constant learning and adapting to new challenges. There were times I wanted to give up. Sometimes, I still wish I could have more free time for the things I love, like traveling, singing, dancing, or painting. But every time I get frustrated, I remind myself of the bigger picture: the potential to make a real difference, to change the lives of patients, and to contribute to the scientific community.</p>
<div style="float: right; margin: 5px;">
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/magic-of-unlocking-secrets-of-our-bodies/fc.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="200"></p>
<figcaption>Francesca in the laboratory.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<p>There’s often a misconception that science is a lonely pursuit, but the truth is, it’s a community effort. I’m deeply grateful to the people who believed in me along the way, including mentors, colleagues, and family. Without their support, I wouldn’t be at Penn today, working to unlock the secrets of the immune system. Here, I’m fortunate to be part of a team that pushes the boundaries of what we know, helping each other with experiments, and sharing with each other successes and challenges of our science. The work we do is driven by a collective belief that, together, we can make the world a better place through discovery and innovation.</p>
<p>As I look ahead to the future of science, I’m filled with excitement not just for what we can accomplish in my lifetime, but for what the next generation of scientists will achieve. One of my greatest joys will be passing on the knowledge I’ve gained to the young scientists who will carry the torch forward. Teaching and mentoring are integral parts of my journey, because, just like others did for me, I want to inspire the next wave of innovators to push the boundaries of what’s possible. Science isn’t just about asking questions – it’s about cultivating the curiosity, creativity, and perseverance to find the answers. It’s about turning what seems like an impossible dream into something tangible, something that can change lives. Whether you’re studying the immune system, exploring the depths of space, or unlocking the secrets of the brain, science is about making the world a better place through knowledge and discovery. Every day in the lab is a new opportunity to learn, to grow, and to make an impact. I feel fortunate to be part of this incredible journey, and I can’t wait to see where it leads. I hope that, through my work, I can share a little bit of that joy and inspire others to be just as excited about the world of science as I am.</p>
<hr>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled" title="About the author" style="">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
About the author
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Francesca is a postdoctoral researcher in the Radiation Oncology department at the University of Pennsylvania. With a master’s in Biology and a PhD in Clinical and Experimental Immunology, when she is not busy trying to find the cure for cancer, Francesca enjoys singing, dancing, painting, cooking, and spending time in nature.</p>
</div>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Curiosity</category>
  <category>Immunology</category>
  <category>Community</category>
  <category>Science Joy</category>
  <guid>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/magic-of-unlocking-secrets-of-our-bodies/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/magic-of-unlocking-secrets-of-our-bodies/conductor.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Worms and Flies and Fungi, Oh My</title>
  <dc:creator>Mikel D. Haggadone, PhD</dc:creator>
  <link>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/worms-flies-fungi-oh-my/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Is scientific research valuable and worth funding if it doesn’t directly impact human health? This question has been vaulted to the forefront of American discourse on science and its support by taxpayer money. I must be honest: as a basic science researcher (we’ll get to what this means in a minute), I’m frustrated by the premise of this question. The answer is so obvious to me: a resounding “YES!”, and my reasoning is both philosophical and practical. I <em>believe</em> – though I recognize and respect opposition to this belief – that there is intrinsic value in knowledge. However, I also <em>know</em> that funding research simply intended to understand more about the natural world has profoundly shaped how we treat and cure disease. As I write this, I feel responsible for acknowledging a personal blind spot while conveying an overlooked and yet critically important sentiment: we, as scientists, have not done a very good job of communicating the importance of our scientific inquisition to you, the public. So, while I am frustrated by the ongoing valuation of my intellectual passions and life’s work as a scientist, I recognize that you deserve to know why what I do is valuable, how it improves your life, and why it’s worthy of taxpayer support.</p>
<p>In this discussion, I want to drive home a very important point: throughout history, scientific curiosity and inquisition – even when not intended to directly impact human health – has created the foundation of knowledge needed to make medical breakthroughs possible today. You might be surprised (and fascinated) to find out that seemingly tangential discoveries made in organisms such as worms, flies, and fungi have fundamentally improved our understanding of human biology and what goes awry during disease. Importantly, at the time of discovery, the value of this research was unknowable, but with time its application has become invaluable. Therefore, funding basic science research does not simply support our curiosity as scientists, but it is also an indispensable long-term investment in your health. Let’s discuss why.</p>
<p>Before we take a step back into history and showcase the impact of some seminal basic science discoveries, let’s first cover relevant terminology. In a very general sense, scientific research can be broken down into two arms: basic research and translational research. Basic science research is, at its very core, driven by curiosity and intended to understand more about the natural world. Its aim isn’t to cure human disease per se, but rather to ask (and answer) the question of how and why things are the way they are. I’m defining this in a very general way to be inclusive of the many different domains of scientific research, but some example questions that researchers may ask and experimentally seek to answer are as follows: How do dietary nutrients impact the way your immune cells function? How do the cells in your body divide and what are the signals that cause them to do this? How does the brain integrate and process sensory information so that your behavior aligns with physiological and environmental needs? What makes plants sensitive or resistant to stress imposed by the environment, whether that be from pathogens (i.e., microbes that can infect and damage them) or extreme weather patterns?</p>
<p>You can imagine the endlessness of this line of questioning, which makes science so exciting! However, perhaps you can also appreciate that while none of these questions alone are posed to directly advance human health, application of the discoveries resulting from them absolutely could and often do. This is where translational science takes center stage. At its core, translational science is the applied arm of research, leveraging our fundamental knowledge of how things work – again, discovered through basic experimentation – to then design studies that are directly intended to improve well-being and/or treat disease. As an example, let’s take the first scientific question posed above, which just so happens to be the line of inquiry guiding my research: How do dietary nutrients impact the way your immune cells function?</p>
<p>To answer this question, I work with both human and mouse samples to experimentally determine what metabolic fuels – the carbohydrates, fats, and amino acids acquired through the foods you eat – are needed for your immune cells to carry out their intended protective functions. When I design experiments in the lab, I don’t do so with any specific disease in mind. Rather, I focus on the exploratory value of gaining knowledge, and I allow my curiosity to conceptually advance the scientific conclusions supported by my data. I, as we say, “follow the science” by simply allowing my empirical observations to instruct the next steps in my experimentation. As a result of this approach, in the three years of my postdoctoral fellowship research, my team has uncovered many fascinating insights into the nutritional safeguards and vulnerabilities of the immune system, and we are becoming well-positioned to begin translating these findings into clinically meaningful contexts like infection and cancer when your immune cells need to do their job in metabolically hostile environments. Will the research I’m doing today save your life tomorrow? Absolutely not, but it does have the potential to revolutionize how we might nutritionally and therapeutically target immune cell metabolism to improve human health in just a matter of years, which is why my work has been so generously funded by organizations and agencies like the American Heart Association and National Institutes of Health.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/worms-flies-fungi-oh-my/mdh-lab.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Mikel in his laboratory conducting an experiment. Credit: Ryan Reiss</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<hr>
<p>Thinking big picture, what I want to underscore here is that this relationship between the basic and translational arms of science is necessarily synergistic. Each arm informs and accelerates the other, and both must <strong>coexist</strong> for medical breakthroughs to happen. It should come as no surprise then that the United States’ financial commitment to basic science research is the reason why we have been a global powerhouse in the health sciences. In essence, your taxpayer support is the lifeline that has created opportunities for scientists like me to transform curiosity into the life-saving tools, technologies, and medicines that in turn benefit you. But don’t just take my word for it, let’s turn to history to show you how.</p>
<p>Most cancer therapies, regardless of their mechanisms of action, share the same primary goal: to cause cancer cells to die. At face value, this seems rather simple, right? The complexity arises from the way that a cancer cell dies, which can come in many different flavors, each with its own set of biological triggers, genetic requirements, and consequences for how surrounding cells interpret and respond to it. These different “flavors” collectively comprise the study of programmed cell death (also referred to as regulated cell death), and many major advances in cancer therapy can be attributed to scientific discoveries that have enhanced our ability to kill tumor cells by targeting an exploitable and suitable regulated cell death modality. What may come as a surprise to you, however, is that the study of programmed cell death originated from basic science research performed using <em>Caenorhabditis elegans</em> (<em>C. elegans</em>), a small roundworm with simple anatomy that has long served as an experimental tool to study how animals develop.</p>
<p>After Dr.&nbsp;Sydney Brenner’s work in the 1960s established <em>C. elegans</em> as a model organism for developmental biology research, the work of two scientists, Drs. John Sulston and H. Robert Horvitz (and others not mentioned here), determined that programmed cell death is a naturally occurring biological process with specific genetic requirements for roundworms to normally grow<span class="citation" data-cites="sulston_post-embryonic_1977 yuan_c_1993"><sup>1,2</sup></span>. Yes, you read that right: during embryogenesis, we need certain cells to die for our organs and tissues to properly develop (otherwise, we’d all have webbed toes and fingers)! This Nobel Prize-winning research set the stage for subsequent discovery of analogous genes and pathways in humans, and it has profoundly shaped our understanding of how and why programmed cell death is both developmentally important and therapeutically exploitable to kill unwanted cells. Let’s zoom out for a second. How remarkable is it that scientific curiosity for the development of a roundworm has so meaningfully advanced our understanding of human biology and influenced how we treat our most challenging diseases? <em>This</em> is the value of basic science.</p>
<p>Research using fruit flies tells a similar tale. We all know that our immune cells detect invading microbes and help to protect us against infectious diseases. The cells comprising our innate immune system (i.e., the body’s first line of defense against pathogens) can do so in a remarkably rapid way. But how do they achieve this? In the late 1980s, a prominent immunologist by the name of Dr.&nbsp;Charles Janeway first theorized that our innate immune system must use receptor molecules that readily detect specific molecular “patterns” intrinsic to invading microbes (e.g., components of their cell wall), thereby making them distinguishable from the patterns that make up our own body. It was an intriguing hypothesis that would explain why our immune system is so good at quickly discerning self (i.e., us) vs.&nbsp;non-self (i.e., pathogenic bugs), but it lacked sound experimental evidence.</p>
<p>In a series of landmark discoveries made throughout the 1990s (including those from one of Dr.&nbsp;Janeway’s postdoctoral trainees, a distinguished immunologist, Dr.&nbsp;Ruslan Medzhitov), scientists cleverly used genetic analyses of a known human immune signaling molecule to uncover similar elements in other species. The hope at the time was to uncover new genetic data that could help point researchers toward the human gene(s) encoding Janeway’s theorized “pattern-recognition receptors”. Shockingly, what they found in <em>Drosophila melanogaster</em>, colloquially known as the fruit fly, was a gene named <em>Toll</em>, which was both genetically similar to the already characterized immune signaling molecule <u>and</u> other human genes previously unknown to researchers. These novel genetic sequences – again, brought to light by comparative genetics in the fruit fly – were subsequently termed Toll-like receptor genes and experimentally demonstrated to encode the very pattern-recognition machinery that Janeway hypothesized would exist throughout the human innate immune system<span class="citation" data-cites="gay_drosophila_1991 medzhitov_human_1997"><sup>3,4</sup></span>. Let’s zoom out again and take a moment to appreciate how amazing this is: because of the herculean efforts made by countless basic scientists to study and functionally characterize genes comprising the fruit fly genome, the stage was set for researchers like Dr. Janeway to uncover the biological basis of pathogen detection and protection against infectious disease. Not only did this research fundamentally advance our basic understanding of the human immune system, but it also fueled the development of therapeutics that improve our ability to fight off pathogens and cancers and dampen the immune response when inflammation goes awry. Here again, <em>this</em> is the value of basic science, and it’s saving lives every single day.</p>
<p>To be candid, if I didn’t have so many experiments to complete at this stage in my career, I’d genuinely love to write a book highlighting more stories like those showcased above – the list is endless. Indeed, not captured here are the many discoveries made using yeast genetics to understand more about how and when our cells divide, or insights into how zebrafish have helped to better characterize the genetic basis of many human diseases. Nevertheless, what I hope you can take away from this essay is that curiosity-driven research has profoundly changed our lives for the better, and it’s simply a consequence of researchers asking the questions, “How?” and “Why?” Research is our passion, and we are indebted to society for supporting our life’s work. Truly, we thank <strong>you</strong>. In turn, I hope you can see the value in what we contribute to you and your health, even when our research questions appear tangential or irrelevant. Because understanding more about the natural world is not only what gives our professional lives purpose and meaning, it is also the foundation of your well-being and the fabric of what has made the United States a leader in biomedical research. Basic science is the lifeblood of medical innovation, and it needs your support now more than ever.</p>
<p>Does this sentiment resonate with you? If so, share your excitement and tell someone what you learned about science today.</p>
<hr>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled" title="About the author" style="">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
About the author
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Mikel Haggadone received his PhD in Immunology from the University of Michigan Medical School in 2021 and is now completing his Postdoctoral Fellowship at the University of Pennsylvania Perelman School of Medicine in the laboratory of Dr.&nbsp;Sunny Shin. In addition to his love for research, Mike is a passionate educator and mentor for Penn’s First Exposure to Research in the Biological Sciences (FERBS) Program, where he has the privilege to support an amazing cohort of undergraduate students in their journey toward becoming future leaders in science and medicine. Outside of academia, Mike cherishes his time with his partner, Dr.&nbsp;Audrey Drotos, in their never-ending pursuit of excellent food and amazing trails to adventure on.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/worms-flies-fungi-oh-my/mdh-trail.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Mikel at the grand canyon. Credit: Adam Hughes, <a href="https://www.preracepodcast.com/">PreRacePodcast Productions</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body" data-entry-spacing="0" data-line-spacing="2">
<div id="ref-sulston_post-embryonic_1977" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">1. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Sulston, J. E. &amp; Horvitz, H. R. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/0012-1606(77)90158-0">Post-embryonic cell lineages of the nematode, <span><em>Caenorhabditis</em></span><span> <em>Elegans</em></span></a>. <em>Developmental Biology</em> <strong>56</strong>, 110–156 (1977).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-yuan_c_1993" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">2. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Yuan, J., Shaham, S., Ledoux, S., Ellis, H. M. &amp; Horvitz, H. R. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/0092-8674(93)90485-9">The <span>C</span>. Elegans cell death gene <span><em>Ced-3</em></span> encodes a protein similar to mammalian interleukin-1<span><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Cbeta"></span>-converting enzyme</a>. <em>Cell</em> <strong>75</strong>, 641–652 (1993).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-gay_drosophila_1991" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">3. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Gay, N. J. &amp; Keith, F. J. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/351355b0">Drosophila <span>Toll</span> and <span>IL-1</span> receptor</a>. <em>Nature</em> <strong>351</strong>, 355–356 (1991).</div>
</div>
<div id="ref-medzhitov_human_1997" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">4. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Medzhitov, R., Preston-Hurlburt, P. &amp; Janeway, C. A. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/41131">A human homologue of the <span>Drosophila Toll</span> protein signals activation of adaptive immunity</a>. <em>Nature</em> <strong>388</strong>, 394–397 (1997).</div>
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Basic Science</category>
  <category>Model Organisms</category>
  <category>History</category>
  <guid>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/worms-flies-fungi-oh-my/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/worms-flies-fungi-oh-my/mdh-lab.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>NIH Intramural Research: from my first job to saving my mom’s life</title>
  <dc:creator>Brooke Wolford</dc:creator>
  <link>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/nih-intramural-first-job-saving-mom/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>On May 25, 2023, I held my mom’s hand while she signed consent forms to enroll as the 94th patient in a clinical trial at the National Institutes of Health (NIH). We were sitting in the NIH Clinical Center, the world’s largest hospital dedicated to clinical research. Some call it the “House of Hope.” We do too.</p>
<p>A decade before the ink dried on those consent forms, I began my first post-college job within sight of the “House of Hope.” I was hired in a full-time research position through the NIH Intramural <a href="https://www.training.nih.gov/research-training/pb/pb/">Postbaccalaureate Program</a>. This is a training opportunity for recent college graduates considering graduate or professional school in healthcare and STEM fields. I worked in Building 50, the Louis Stokes Laboratories, which houses the laboratories of the National Human Genome Research Institute, one of 27 Institutes and Centers of the NIH. These Institutes compose the NIH Intramural Program, which is supported by 11% of the NIH budget and funds the nearly 6,000 scientists on the NIH main campus in Bethesda, Maryland, and other smaller NIH campuses across the US.</p>
<p>I spent two exciting and impactful years working in the laboratory of Dr. Francis Collins, the NIH Director at the time. With my mentors, I studied how genetic variation can lead to Type 2 Diabetes. This experience laid the groundwork for my career as a geneticist, and, unbeknownst to me at the time, it prepared me for my role as a caregiver of an NIH patient. I knew how to search <a href="https://clinicaltrials.gov/">ClinicalTrials.gov</a> for treatment opportunities. I trusted her team of providers. My familiarity with the NIH and biomedical research enabled me to advocate for and support my mom during this journey.</p>
<p>The world’s experts on my mom’s rare disease, lymphomatoid granulomatosis (LYG), work at the National Cancer Institute of the NIH. In the summer of 2023, they gave my mom life-saving, but grueling, chemotherapy, to rid her body of the rapidly multiplying cells caused by Epstein Barr Virus (EBV). This is the virus that causes mono and lives dormant in about 90% of us. In my mom, Epstein Barr Virus is active and causing problems. Because it is a rare disease, it has taken over 30 years to enroll enough patients to really understand the way this disease works and how to treat it.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/nih-intramural-first-job-saving-mom/bnw-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Brooke and her mom after she completed her last of 6 rounds of chemotherapy at the NIH Clinical Center.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<hr>
<p>Before this clinical trial, scientific publications established the median survival for LYG as 14 months, because it wasn’t clear how to treat these patients. When she was diagnosed, this trial felt like our only hope. Her private insurance was unlikely to cover medicine not yet demonstrated to be the standard of care for LYG. Determining standard of care for a rare disease is time consuming and expensive! This is the kind of life-changing work the NIH Intramural Program supports. Led by Dr.&nbsp;Christopher Melani, the clinical trial successfully established a set of treatments as standard of care, publishing a median survival of 12.1 years<span class="citation" data-cites="melani_interferon_2023"><sup>1</sup></span>. This result will facilitate better treatment of LYG at hospitals across the country and globally.</p>
<p>Clinical trials like the one that saved my mom fall under the NIH’s Intramural Research program. Thanks to taxpayer dollars, my mom’s treatment was paid for. So was the fuel she used to drive the 7 hours to and from rural North Carolina. Budget cuts have reduced the amount she is reimbursed for her accommodations in Maryland, but this is the price we will pay for more years together. For NIH patients facing hardships, <a href="https://www.friendsatnih.org/">the Friends of Patients at the NIH</a> is a charitable organization that helps with emotional, financial, and logistical support.</p>
<p>Fast forward to January 2025, and my mom was one treatment into her second clinical trial at the NIH. After a year in remission, her disease was back, so the doctors were trying something new. As the new Presidential administration came to Washington, Executive Orders caused communication and travel bans, as well as funding freezes at the NIH. We were incredibly concerned how new policy might affect her ability to continue treatment. As of now, her trial is running as expected. However, the NIH Intramural Postbaccalaureate Program which once employed me, and provides valuable training to the next generation of our nation’s scientists and physicians, is paused pending guidance from the Department of Health and Human Services.</p>
<p>As a scientist and a daughter of a rare disease warrior, the NIH Intramural Research Program has changed my life. It is my deepest wish that the NIH continues to be a model of excellence for biomedical research by treating patients, training scientists, making discoveries, stimulating the economy, and providing hope for decades to come. I hope the “House of Hope” will be there for you, too, if you one day need it.</p>
<hr>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled" title="About the author" style="">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
About the author
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p><a href="https://bnwolford.github.io/">Brooke</a> is a Marie Skłodowska-Curie Postdoctoral Fellow at the Norwegian University of Science and Technology. She spends her days studying the genetics of heart disease, snuggling her Basenjis, and learning to speak Norwegian. Snakker du norsk?</p>
</div>
</div>
<p><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/nih-intramural-first-job-saving-mom/bnw-2.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>




<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-bibliography"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body" data-entry-spacing="0" data-line-spacing="2">
<div id="ref-melani_interferon_2023" class="csl-entry">
<div class="csl-left-margin">1. </div><div class="csl-right-inline">Melani, C. <em>et al.</em> <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/S2352-3026(23)00029-7">Interferon alfa-2b in patients with low-grade lymphomatoid granulomatosis and chemotherapy with <span>DA-EPOCH-R</span> in patients with high-grade lymphomatoid granulomatosis: An open-label, single-centre, phase 2 trial</a>. <em>The Lancet Haematology</em> <strong>10</strong>, e346–e358 (2023).</div>
</div>
</div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>NIH</category>
  <category>Clinical Trials</category>
  <category>Family</category>
  <guid>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/nih-intramural-first-job-saving-mom/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/nih-intramural-first-job-saving-mom/bnw-1.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Introducing Your Neighborhood Scientist</title>
  <dc:creator>Audrey Drotos</dc:creator>
  <link>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/introducing-your-neighborhood-scientist/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Hello!</p>
<p>My name is Audrey, and I’m a neuroscientist. I study brain cells: how they talk to each other, what they’re saying, and how they help us figure out what’s going on in our environments.</p>
<p>I started this newsletter because I’m increasingly concerned about how science and medical research is viewed by the public. There’s been a shift over the last few years in how I hear people talk about science, and it’s at odds with what I see and experience in my day-to-day life as a researcher. I feel so excited about the amount of progress being made in the scientific community, from treatments for HIV and pediatric cancers to new vaccines for RSV and cancer, but I sense a growing unease with these same discoveries amongst the general public, with an increase in discussion of conspiracy theories (like the myth that vaccines cause autism), a decrease in the number of people who support public health measures backed by science (like fluoride in our drinking water), and general growing distrust in the scientific and medical communities.</p>
<p>I’m sure there are many factors at play that have widened this chasm between scientists and non-scientists, but I think one is a misunderstanding of how science works: how basic science informs medical breakthroughs, how science is funded in the US, and the role that pharmaceutical companies and medical professionals play. I think most people would be surprised to hear that much of what we know about human genetics comes from studying yeast and worms, or that the US federal government funds upwards of 90% of the research happening at universities across the US, both public and private.</p>
<p>In addition, I think another big driver of this gap between scientists and the general public is a misunderstanding of who scientists are. I’ve worked in academia for the last nine years of my life, and the people I work with are some of the most compassionate, hard-working, dedicated individuals, who sacrifice many years of their lives to bring new advancements into the world that will make our lives better. As I read Facebook comments and see the rhetoric on TV, I often find myself wishing I could just show people the scientists I know: I wish I could bring you to lab and show you the people I work with every day, show you how hard they are working, and show you how the work they do makes your life better and our communities stronger.</p>
<p>Your Neighborhood Scientist is my initiative to do just that: to tell the world how the scientists in your neighborhoods are working hard—just like you—to leave a positive mark on this world. I started this newsletter because I believe that we can work together to show the world that science is critical to the health and well-being of our communities. Changing this rhetoric is no small task, and I think it starts with information: how does this all work? How does the work scientists do every day, funded by taxpayers, eventually end up handed to you over the counter at your local pharmacy in a paper bag that contains life-saving medication? How does it strengthen our economy? How does it enhance our national defense and emergency preparedness?</p>
<p>I also realize that if you’re reading this newsletter, you’re likely someone who is somewhat interested in science. I probably don’t have to convince you too much that we should fund basic science research, and that scientists are incredible, genuine people who are trying to make the world a better place. But why do you think that? Maybe it’s because you understand the intricacies of science, and you know about NIH institutes and CAR-T cell pathways. Or maybe not: most likely, you believe in science because you know and trust me, Audrey, your neighborhood scientist. People’s beliefs are not informed by facts and information: they are informed by feelings and trust.</p>
<p>In our newsletter, we’ll work to fill the science information gap by stressing the importance of basic science research and providing information about how it works, and I hope that you do learn more about the work scientists do. But to me, it’s not important if you remember specific details, like what an indirect rate is at the NIH. What’s important is that you feel inspired to tell other people that know and trust you about how important you think science is. Perhaps over time they might even become convinced that they, too, should advocate for scientists and good science policy. The goal is to provide the knowledge that scientists are working hard to make the world a better place and use this as a vehicle to spread positive feelings and trust surrounding science, because these are the things that change people’s minds.</p>
<p>I don’t know what will ultimately happen with this journey, but if you read all the way through: thank you. Tell someone who trusts you about science today, and see you in a couple weeks.</p>
<hr>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note no-icon callout-titled" title="About the author" style="">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon no-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
About the author
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Dr.&nbsp;Audrey Drotos is a Neuroscientist at the University of Pennsylvania where she studies how we hear. She is a founder of Your Neighborhood Scientist. Outside of science and writing, she enjoys long-distance trail running, thrifting vintage jackets, buying really good apples at the farmer’s market, and curling up with a great book, preferably one by Ed Yong.</p>
<p><img src="https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/introducing-your-neighborhood-scientist/acd.jpg" class="img-fluid"></p>
</div>
</div>



 ]]></description>
  <category>Intro</category>
  <category>Policy</category>
  <guid>https://neighborhoodscientist.org/posts/2025/introducing-your-neighborhood-scientist/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
